<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eight speeches spoken in Guild-Hall, upon Thursday night, Octob. 27. 1642. Printed in the same order they were spoken, one after the other, by the Lo: VVharton, Mr Strode, the Earl of Pembroke, the Earl of Holland, the Lo: Say. Also a letter from Mr. Secretary Nicholas to the Earle of Cumberland.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E124_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5746</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872892</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156165</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83741)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156165)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E124[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eight speeches spoken in Guild-Hall, upon Thursday night, Octob. 27. 1642. Printed in the same order they were spoken, one after the other, by the Lo: VVharton, Mr Strode, the Earl of Pembroke, the Earl of Holland, the Lo: Say. Also a letter from Mr. Secretary Nicholas to the Earle of Cumberland.</title>
                  <author>Wharton, Philip Wharton, Baron, 1613-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 9-22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Cole at the signe of the Glove neere the Royall Exchange, overagainst [sic] the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156165:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156165:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EIGHT SPEECHES Spoken in GVILD-HALL, <hi>Upon Thurſday night, Octob.</hi> 27. 1642. Printed in the ſame order they were ſpoken, one after the other, <hi>BY The Lo:</hi> VVharton, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Strode, <hi>The Earl of</hi> Pembroke, <hi>The Earl of</hi> Holland, <hi>The Lo:</hi> Say. Alſo a Letter from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Secretary <hi>Nicholas</hi> to the Earle of <hi>Cumberland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: <hi>Printed for</hi> PETER COLE at the ſigne of the Glove neere the <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> overagainſt the Conduit. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:156165:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156165:2"/>
            <head>The Lord <hi>VVharton</hi> his Speech.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lords, and you the Aldermen, and the Commons of this City, in a buſines of this very great conſequence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, it was very well known to my Lo: General, that you could not but be full of great expectations, and my Lord had according to his duty taken care for to give information to the Parl. to thoſe that had ſent him, of what had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded; in the very next place it was his particular reſpect to this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to my Lo: Mayor, the Aldermen, the Common Councel, and all the Commons of this City, that they might likewiſe be acquainted with the ſucceſſe of that buſineſſe, towards which they themſelves had bin at ſo much expences, and had ſhewed ſo much love and kindneſſe in all the proceedings of this buſineſſe, for that purpoſe, becauſe that Letters might be uncertaine, and might miſcarry, there being great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terception of them, the Forces of the Armies being cloſe together, my Lord thought fit to ſend M. <hi>Strode,</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and my ſelfe, and certainly whatſoever ſhall be related by us to you, it wil be good news, or elſe we ſhould not willingly have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the bringing of it, and for the truth of it, though we already heare that there are thoſe that have ſo much malignity as to oppoſe it, yet the certainty of it wil clear it ſelfe, and therefore there ſhall need no Apologies to be made, but that which ſhal be ſaid to you, ſhal be the truth, and nothing but the truth, in a very cleere way of relation of what hath paſt.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I ſhall open to you as neere as I can, as it comes within my memory, thoſe things of circumſtance which are worthy the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king notice of, and one in the firſt place ſhal be, the occaſion why ſo many of the Forces were not then upon the place, which you wil find to be upon very good ground and reaſon, for the preſervation of the Countries that were behind, and of this City, which is he particular thing in the care, and now under the deligence of my Lo: Generall, to preſerve. There was left at <hi>Hereford</hi> which lies upon the confines of Wales, a Regiment of Foot under the command of my Lo: of <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and a Troop or two of Horſe, that the power of Wales might not fal in upon Glouceſterſhire, and upon the river of Severn, and ſo upon the Weſt. There was likewiſe left at <hi>Worceſter</hi> (which you all know how it is ſeated upon the river of Severne, and what advantage it hath to interce Pt all force that ſhal come from Shrewsbury down into the Weſt) a Regiment of my Lord Saint <hi>Iohns,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Merricks.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156165:3"/>There was for the ſafety of <hi>Coventry</hi> (for that was a town it was likely the King might have faln upon) the Regiment of my Lo: <hi>Rochford;</hi> but it ſeems that his Excellence the E. of Eſſex his Army did ſo quickly come up to the Kings, that the King thought it no way fit or advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious for him to ſpend any time upon thoſe places, for certainly they would have very quickly been relieved, ſo that the King ſtipt by <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> and <hi>Coventry,</hi> which otherwiſe we conceive they were towns he had as good an eye upon as any other towns in the whole Kingdome, excepting this. There was likewiſe occaſion upon the ſuddennes of my Lords march, 2. Regiments of Foot, one under the command of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman you all know, Col: <hi>Hampden,</hi> and the other under the command of Col: <hi>Grantham,</hi> with ſome 10. or 12. Troops of Horſe, &amp; theſe were but one dayes march behind, &amp; upon the occaſion of bringing up ſome powder, and ammunition, and Artillery, which my Lord would not ſtay for purpoſely upon his diligence &amp; deſire that there ſhould not be an houre loſt in purſuing after that Armie, and that he might make all haſte in comming up to this town, and his deſire to make haſte to keep with that Army was ſuch, that he kept for two or three dayes together a dayes march before that Armie; and ſo there being another Regiment lodged in <hi>Banbury,</hi> occaſionally for their own ſafety, there was with my Lord when this battle was fought upon the Lords day, 11. Regiments of Foot, and about the number of 35. or 37. or 40. troops of Horſe; that which makes me ſay this to you, is partly for your ſatisfactions, that you may know the reaſons of the things are paſt, and partly that you may give the more glory to God for his bleſſing, and for his preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that remnant of the Army which was together, beeing about 11. Regiments of Foot, and a matter of 35. or 40. troops of Horſe.</p>
            <p>Upon the Saterday at night, upon a very long march (for they came not in til 9. or 10. a clock at night) the Armie came to <hi>Konton,</hi> &amp; the next morning about 7. a clock (though all that night there was news came that the King was going to <hi>Banbury</hi>) we had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain information he was comming down a hil, which is called <hi>Edge Hill,</hi> which hath ſome advantage by nature for Forts, &amp; breaſt-works, and ſuch things as thoſe are; and that Hil the Kings Armie came down at that time (that Armie which goes under the pretence of being raiſed for him, and by his authority, for and againſt the Parl.) his Armie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down, my Lo: of Eſſex preſently drew out into the Field, and drew his Armie into a place of as good advantage as poſſibly he could, though the other Armie had the advantage by the hil, which they were poſſeſſed of before, and at the beginning of the day the wind it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:156165:3"/>us, and was for the advantage of the other Armie. The prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on both ſides was for the making of them ready for fight, and the Kings comming down the hil was ſo long, that there was nothing done til 4. in the afternoone. And Gentleman I ſhal tel you the worſt as wel as the beſt, that you may know all, and that when you have known the worſt, you may find it in your judgments, to give the more praiſe to God for his mercy, after there was ſo much probabilitie of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch an ill ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>After that we had ſhot</hi> 2. <hi>or</hi> 3. <hi>Peeces of Ordnance, they began for to ſhoot ſome of theirs, and truly not long after, before there was any neere execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there was</hi> 3. <hi>or</hi> 4. <hi>of our Regiments fairely ran away. I ſhall name you the particulars, and afterwards name you thoſe that did the extraordinary ſervice, whereof you will find thoſe of this City to have been very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary inſtruments. There were that ran away, Sir</hi> Wil: Fairfax <hi>his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Sir</hi> Henry Cholmleys, <hi>and my Lord</hi> Mandevils, <hi>and to ſay the plain truth my own. Theſe ran away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gentlemen, you ſee by this time I am like to tell you the truth, I hope of every thing, but yet I muſt ſay this, that though they did ſo, yet I hope there will be very convenient &amp; very good number of them got together again, that may ſhew themſelves in better condition, and better way of ſervice then yet they have done, I hope ſo, and by the bleſſing of God it may be ſo, for they are but young ſouldiers, and we have ſeene very good experience of ſome of them, that have this laſt battaile done very extraordinary and gallant ſervice, not long after there was a charge upon the left wing of the horſe, and there I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there was a matter of 18, or 19. Troopes, and truly I cannot ſay they did ſo well as they ſhould, though I hope there are not many of them cut off neither, but that they will be brought together again to do very good ſervice hereafter, but ſo it is, they had the worſt of it, and by this you will ſee that at the beginning of the day wee might thinke it would not prove ſo well as it pleaſed God it did afterwards in the cloſe of the day, for foure troopes were divided, and one part of the horſe were not in good order, but it pleaſed God now to ſhew himſelfe, for after they had paſt the left wing of our horſe, I cannot ſay it was in any hands but Gods own providence, the horſe that had paſt through them flolowed them in part, and went to the Towne where all our baggage was; the baggage of the officers and the private perſons of the Army, not they of the Artilery, but the Colonels carts and the Captains carts, and ſuch proviſion as that, and there they tooke a baite upon our pillage, and fell a plundering, all that while
<pb facs="tcp:156165:4"/>the reſt of the Army was a fighting, and indeede my Lord Generall had ſome more loſſe then ordinary by ſome clothes and money he had there, but we may thanke God they were away, for thereby the reſt of the Army had the better oportunity to do that ſervice they did.</p>
            <p>My Lord Generall himſelfe upon this extremity did begin to ſhew himſelfe to be more then an ordinary man, and indeede I thinke more then I have heard tell of any man, for he charged up at ſeverall times, once with his own troope of horſe as I remember, but I am ſure with his own Regiment of foote which was raiſed here in Eſſex, and though ſo many ill paſſages happened before, with his owne provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and encouragement, and the encouragement of others, his own troope of horſe fell upon the Kings owne Regiment, (which they had moſt hopes of) which they called the red Regiment, after a ſore and bitter fight (for to give them their due, they fought very well, thoſe of my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his regiment, and thoſe horſe I ſpake of before) they killed the Kings Standard bearer Sir <hi>Edward Varney,</hi> they tooke the Kings Standard which was raiſed up againſt the Parliament, and it was brought my Lo: General, and he delivered it to a ſervant which was not ſo carefull as he ought to have beene, but it was not taken by force but by the careleſneſſe and negligence of ſome perſons, but it was gotten by force and loſt thus. They tooke likewiſe the Kings General priſoner; and caried him away, they tooke priſoner my Lord Generals Sonne, my Lo: <hi>Willoughby,</hi> that perſon you have heard ſo much of, and beene ſo wel acquainted with here, Col. <hi>Lunsford</hi> which ſhould have had the Tower, hee was likewiſe taken priſoner, and his brother ſlaine, and Sir <hi>Edward Stradling</hi> priſoner, and divers others of quality, My Lo: <hi>Awberney,</hi> and Col: <hi>Vavaſour,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edward Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy</hi> a Scotchman of great quality, while theſe were upon this ſervice I muſt give the right to divers other of the Officers of the horſe which were upon the right wing, that they did extraordinary ſervice to, that was my Lord of <hi>Bedford</hi> himſelfe who did very galantly, and Sir <hi>Will. Belfore</hi> the late Lieutenant of the Tower, Sir <hi>Phillip Stapelton,</hi> and all the troope which formerly had been under ſome other kinde of report, they did extraordinary ſervice, kept entirely to their charge, and though they were long under the power of the other Canons there were ſome 17. ſhot of Canon ſhot againſt them, and they ſtood ſtil, and God be thanked not a man of them hurt, yet there was likewiſe very extraordinary ſervice performed by my Lo: <hi>Gray</hi> and Sir <hi>Arther Hazelrig,</hi> who indeede was a helpe for to give a great turne to the day by cutting off a Regiment of the Kings which was called
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156165:4"/>the blew Regiment, and there were many other Gentlemen of great worth, that did very extraordinary ſervice, too, I would not have you underſtand that others did not do it, becauſe I remember not their names for I ſpeak to you now but on the ſudden, but there were divers others did very great ſervice, onely theſe I have named that come to my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, and you will heare more of the reſt upon other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; upon the cloſe of the day we know it for certain, that the beſt Regiment of the Kings was cut off, and the next his beſt Regiment, which was that was under my Lord of Linſey; there was all the priſoners taken I told you off, there were thoſe perſons of quallitie ſlain I told you off, and there was as we conceive (this I tell you upon informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as we conceive, and are in formed by the Countrie men that ſaw them burie the dead next day, and bring them up into heaps, there was as is informed, and conceived) about 3000 of theirs ſlain: and we cannot beleeve, nor we cannot have any information, to give us reaſon to beleeve that there was ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve 300 of ours ſlain; And this was to be obſerved of Gods providence in this dayes worke, that though it began ſo improbably, yet before the cloſe of the night, which was two houres, (for they began to fight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but about four a clocke,) we had got the ground, that they were upon, we had gotten the winde, and we do not know, nor by information conceive, that there was twenty men of ours killed, by all the Kings Cannon; when it was night that there could be no more fighting, we drew our forces together, and ſo likewiſe did the King; they were then but at a reaſonable diſtance, it may be three times, or ſix times or ſome ſuch diſtance of this room; but in the night the forces of the King withdrew up towards the hill from whence they came; and my Lord Generall amongſt others ſent my ſelf for to bring on thoſe forces which I told you were a dayes march behinde, (which was Collonell <hi>Hamden,</hi> and Collonell <hi>Grantham,</hi> and thoſe troops of horſe, and the Artillery,) and ſent to bring them up to him; and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156165:5"/>about one a clocke at night, or two a clocke, thoſe forces came to my Lord Generall, and joyned with the reſt of the Armie, and when the King had drawne his forces up the hill, my Lord Generall drew us a matter of half a mile, or three quarters of a mile further from the hill, that he might be out of the power of the Cannon; there we ſtood to our arms all the night, and in the morning drew our ſelves out againe into the fields but we heard no more newes of the other army, more then we ſaw ſome ſcattering men, of ſome three or four troopes of horſes on the top of the hill, which came to burie the dead, and take away ſome of their Cannon, and ſuch things as thoſe were, but they came no more down the hill, neither that day, nor on tueſday, though there were divers reports came to us in the Armie, and I beleeve came hither, that there was fighting on Monday, and Teuſday, yet there was no fighting, for the King kept on the top of the hill, and we came away on Teuſday at four a clocke; ſo that we can aſſure you there was no more action, then was on the Lords day;</p>
            <p>Gentlemen I ſhall after I have declared this narration to you ſay no more then this, that certainly my Lord Generall himſelf hath deſerved as much in this ſervice, for his pains, &amp; for his care, and for the particular ſucceſſe that was upon it, as truly I think ever any Gentleman did; and in the next place, that as God of his owne immediate providence did thus declare himſelfe for the owning of his owne cauſe, ſo you will not forget to apply your ſelves to God, to give him the glory, and to entreat his bleſſing upon the future ſucceſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:156165:5"/>
            <head>Maſter STRODE his <hi>SPEECH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GEntlemen all, as this noble Lord hath tolde you, my Lord Generall hath ſent him up to you, to give you a clear information of what was done: he hath given you ſo cleare a one, that there is little left for me to ſay to you, only my atteſtation, and that needes not, had that beene all, I ſhould have ſaid nothing but in the Innumeration of thoſe regiments that did run away, and of his owne, I muſt needs ſay thus much, when they all were away, he ſtayd with us in the ſervice all that night, this hold it my dutie to this honourable perſon, it was modeſty in himſelfe to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</p>
            <p>I ſhall crave leave a little further, to make you ſome obſervation, that as God did this great worke, and we aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe to him the honour, ſo you will looke upon the perſons by whom he did it; In the firſt place, you have heard when as it was 1000 to one but that we had loſt the day by running away of the troope of horſe, and the four Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, and then the Generall did draw up his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and then did God begin in them to ſhew his owne worke, and it was not onely in them, but by a Regiment raiſed in Eſſex and another Regiment raiſed in this Cittie under the command of maſter <hi>Hollis,</hi> and another Regiment of my Lord <hi>Brookes,</hi> which had the day upon them; theſe were the men that were ignominiouſly, reproached by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156165:6"/>name of Round-heads, and by theſe Round-heads did God ſhew himſelfe a moſt glorious God; And truly (Gentlemen) they that will report to you the Number of our dead, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then we have reported them to you, muſt finde them many miles from the Armie, and then they were men that run away ſo far, that it was no matter who killed them; for our men that we could finde any where about the place, we cannot finde in all (nor thinke) above 300, and you'll ſay, they were well loſt that ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away; the boldeſt men of them that ſtood were few loſt, and they that were ſo loſt, were loſt with a great deale of honour; and I beleeve, you will have them in more reputation, then they that live and run away; ſo that truly I can ſay no more to you, in ſuch a cauſe as this is, that you have undertaken with your purſes, and with your perſons, God hath ſhewed himſelf with us be you but couragious and we never need doubt it; and ſo we ſay all.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Earl of PEMBROOK his <hi>SPEECH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY Lord Maior, and you Gentlemen of the City, I am commanded, and the reaſon that makes me trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you at this time with ſaying any thing, is by reaſon of a Letter I have received from the Committee, which I think is a Letter of ſome conſequence, and fitting for you to ſee; otherwiſe I am ſo ill a Speaker after ſuch a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration made to you, I have not the boldneſſe to ſay any thing to you: but truely though I ſay little, and have a bad tongue, yet I have ever had ſo good a heart to this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that I ſhall ever live and die in it.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:156165:6"/>
            <p>Gentlemen, you have ſhew'd your ſelves like brave and noble Citizens; you have done it with that nobleneſſe, with that alacrity, with that love to God, King, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that none of your Anceſtors before you never ſhewed more love, nor care, nor zeal, nor performed that you have done better: I have onely this to ſay to you, If the times are ſuch (not that I think there is any great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill in the Kings Army now, for they have told you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but truth) yet when you have ſeen this Letter, you will finde there is very good cauſe for you to crown this work, which muſt be by following it, with the ſame zeal, love, care, and nobleneſſe, and alacrity, which if you do, you may well crown your ſelves with the name of a glorious City; and none more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Letter</head>
            <head type="sub">For his Excellency the Earl of <hi>CUMBERLAND,</hi> Lord Ganerall of His Majeſties Forces in the North.</head>
            <p>MY very good Lord, your Lordſhips of the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of this month I have received by <hi>Stockdale,</hi> and have read it to his Majeſty; who willed me to fignifie to your Lordſhip, that he is well pleaſed with your Lordſhips continuing of the Sheriff in his place, albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he ſent a Writ for his diſcharge: his Majeſty takes a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall notice of your Lordſhips vigilancy and care, in the truſt he hath repoſed in your Lordſhip; as he hath by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny very gracious expreſſions declared at ſeverall times, openly, upon conference of your buſineſſe in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156165:7"/>Your Lordſhips care of my Lady Dutcheſſe of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> is (I aſſure you) very well taken by his Maieſty. Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton,</hi> and other Gentlemen in the Weſt, have raiſed ten thouſand Horſe and Foot, with which they have already diſarmed all perſons in <hi>Cornwall</hi> that are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to the King: they have taken <hi>Lanceſton,</hi> and are marching into <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> to diſarm the diſaffected there; and ſo intend to come to meet the King at <hi>London:</hi> here are alſo in <hi>Wales</hi> about ſix or ſeven thouſand men levyed for the King, which are to be under Marqueſſe <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> that will be ready upon all occaſions, to come to his Maieſty; but we hope he will not need their help, having given the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſuch a blow, as they will make no haſte again to adventure themſelves in that cauſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Anointed: I ſhall referre your Lordſhip to the relation of the Bearer, for the particulars. To mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his Maieſty marcheth towards <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Oxford.</hi> I am ſo full of buſineſſe, as I muſt crave your Lordſhips pardon that I write ſo briefly; but I am nevertheleſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edgeſcot, Northampton,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 24. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips most humble Servant, Edward Nicholas.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:156165:7"/>
            <head>The Earl of HOLLAND his <hi>SPEECH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY Lord Maior, and you Gentlemen of the City, It is more by obedience then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that I ſay any thing to you at this time; my Lords and the Comittee command me, and therefore I ſhall obey them: That that I ſhall ſay to you, is to obſerve in the Relation that this noble Lord hath made: In the firſt part of it, what deliverance God hath ſent you, that in a danger, and indeed ſuch as I am confident all that were there believe the Cauſe of Religion, and Liberty, and all loſt; you ſaw what a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent turn it had, ſuch a one, as if it did not give them the victory, it gave them the advantage, that is certain; and truely a very great one, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when it was taken from ſo unhappy a condition as they were likely to be in, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God hath ſhewed us what a danger might have fallen upon us: And certainly it is, becauſe every man ſhould conſider in that danger, what he might have ſuffered, and what his cauſe might have ſuffered, and to give you all by this, warning, That as he hath now begun to deliver you onely by his hand, and by his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156165:8"/>power, he will expect that you will expreſſe ſuch a thankfulneſſe to him for it, as now to make his Cauſe your work, and to do it with your hands, boldly, and with courage: For this Letter that you heard read now, you ſee what is threatned againſt you; the leaſt that you muſt expect, is this great Army of the Kings, that certainly by the diſpoſitions of thoſe that command it, and have great power in it, you muſt know what to expect, and what to truſt to; they intend you no leſſe (and that is to be believed) then the deſtroying of the City, your perſons, and the preying upon your fortunes: This is not all, you ſee that if this doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, or be not powerfull enough, an Army muſt come from the weſt, the preparation of another in the North from all parts of the Kingdom, the ſword is drawn againſt you: and truly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe ill intentions that they certainly have, it is the wiſeſt courſe they can take; for in your City is the ſtrength of the kingdom indeed; it is not onely the life, but the ſoul of it; if they can deſtroy you here, the reſt of the Kingdome muſt all ſubmit and yeeld, and in that yeelding muſt give over the maintenance of all that is moſt dear to them: Therefore if you will now conſider how God hath ſhewed you firſt, that he hath kept the firſt blow from you, by deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of you indeed from ſuch an immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t danger, as it could not be believed it could have been
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156165:8"/>recover'd, but by himſelfe, and by the power of his hand; this may give you juſt encouragement to purſue al things that are for his glory, &amp; for the defence of your Religion, and his cauſe, I am confident, as you will doe it with thankfulnes, and duty, and ſincerity to him, ſo in wiſedom, and reaſon you will (ſeeing with threatnings there are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, you will defend your ſelves, and your families; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture directs you to it, as well as piety; we only recommend this to you, that you may but know it, and take it into your thoughts, and into your hearts, and then wee are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident your hearts will be rayſed with ſo much piety, with ſo much courage, and with ſo much reſolution, as you wil defend your ſelves, and in defending your ſelves, defend us, the Parliament, and the Kingdome, you may do it, you have power, and we expect it from your affections. <hi>Finis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Lord Say and Seale his ſpeech.</head>
            <p>MY Lords and Gentlemen, that little that I have to ſay, ſhal not be to ſet forth your approaching dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but I ſhall rather apply my ſelf to ſtir up your ſpirits, to incourage you, and to ſettle this opinion in you, that if you be not wanting unto your ſelves, which cannot be imagined in this cauſe, you will have no cauſe to feare danger; it cannot bee doubted by that which you have heard, but that theſe malignant miſcheivous counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and theſe men of deſperate fortunes that they have gather'd to them, and into whoſe hands they have put our King, that their intentions are, that this rich glorious City ſhould bee deliver'd up as a prey, as a reward to them for their treaſon againſt the Kingdome and the Parliament, and that your lives ſhould ſatisfie their malice, your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156165:9"/>wives, your daughters, their luſt, and religion it ſelfe the deareſt thing of all others to us, ſhould be made merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize off, to invite Papiſts, to invite forreigners. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their intentions let no mans heart bee diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, you have power enough in your hands, to bring all this wickednes upon their own heads, through Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; if you will uſe your hands, if you will hold them up to ſerve your God, to defend the true religion of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, to defend your lives, to defend this Kingdome and the Parliament, you need not feare any thing that can bee done by this broken Army, nor feare thoſe things, that are here written in this letter, nor thoſe things that are falſely buzzed abroad by a malignant party, in your City to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze you, there is no feare of danger, but in ſecurity, in ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill; and therefore if you will be ſtirred up (as I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt, we cannot imagine you will) to do that that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man, both by the law of God, and by the law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in this caſe will bee induced to doe, through Gods bleſſing, you ſhall both honour God, maintaine the true Religion, ſave this Kingdome, ſave the Parliament, and Crowne your good beginnings that God hath pleaſed to ſhew himſelfe unto us in; this is now not a time for men to thinke with themſelvs, that they will be in their ſhops, to get a little mony, this is a time to do that that you doe; in common dangers, let every man take his weapons in his hand, let him offer himſelf willingly to ſerve his God, and to maintaine true Religion; you may remember what God ſaith by the Prophet, <hi>my heart is ſet upon thoſe people, that are willing to offer themſelves willingly upon the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> let every man therefore ſhut up his ſhop, let him take his musket, let him offer himſelf readily, and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let him not thinke with himſelfe, who ſhall pay me,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156165:9"/>but rather think this, I'le come forth to ſave the Kingdom, to ſerve my God, to maintaine his true Religion, to ſave the Parliament, to ſave this noble city, and when this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is overcome, I'le truſt the State, that they will have a regard unto whatſoever may be fit, either for my repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any loſſe; or for my reward; doe as you doe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon dangers, when there is a fire, men aske not who ſhall pay him his daies wages, but every man comes forth of his doores, helpes to quench the fire, brings a bucket, if he have one, borrowes one of his neighbour if he have not, when the fire is quenched, then the City will regard to repayre any man that hath ſuffered all day, that doe you, every one bring forth his Arms, if he have it, if he have it not, let him borrow Armes of his neighbour, or hee ſhall bee armed from the State; let every man arme himſelfe, and arme his apprentizes, and come forth with boldneſſe and with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and with cheerefulneſſe, and doubt not but God will aſſiſt you; for though you bee concerned in all you have, yet this is Gods cauſe, that ſhould be your incouragement, for they are Papiſts, they are Atheiſts, that come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you; they come indeed in the firſt and principle aim they have to deſtroy Religion; Papiſts are invited, they have Commiſſions, are theſe men that ſhould defend the Proteſtant Religion, when they are Papiſts, and recuſants. Therefore if that you ſhall come forth, God will go forth with you, he will fight for you, he will ſave you, but how? he wil not ſave you without your ſelves; you may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what was ſaid, <hi>Curſe ye Meroſh, becauſe they came not out to help the Lord againſt the mighty;</hi> he needs not your helpe, but he will uſe your ſervice, that he may bleſſe you, and therefore let every man be incouraged, let him ſhew his readineſſe, let hiw ſhew his forwardneſſe; remember
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156165:10"/>what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Heare O Iſrael, God is with you, ſo long as you are with him,</hi> the Lord will bee with you in this cauſe, for it his cauſe, but then you muſt ſhew your ſelves ready to bee with him, but I need not uſe theſe ſpeeches to thoſe that have expreſſed already, ſo much affection as you have done, I ſhall onely incourage you to go on; bee not daunted, let not malignant parties that goe up and downe, and would goe about to informe you, that there are theſe feares, and theſe dangers, let them not make you be wanting to your ſelves, feare them not at all; I ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with this, that that good King ſaid, <hi>up and be doing, and the Lord will be with you. Finis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Lord Wharton his ſecond ſpeech</head>
            <p>GEntlemen, I ſhall trouble you but with a word or two the one is upon part of that narrative, which I began withal, wherein truly I take my ſelf to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beholding to that Gentleman that ſpoke after me, that he did not forget to inform you of the extraordinary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that God beſtowed upon the courage of honeſt, pious, and religious men; for truely there was very few that did any extraordinary ſervice, but ſuch as had a mark of religion upon them: That which I omitted to tell you, was this, that one great cauſe of the preſervation, and of the ſucceſſe of that day, was the barbarouſneſſe, and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity of Prince <hi>Robert,</hi> and his Troops, who while wee were a fighting, not only pillaged of the baggage (which was but a poore imployment!) but moſt barbarouſly killed Country-men that came in with their teemes, and women, and children that were with them; this I thinke comes not amiſſe to tel you, becauſe you may ſee, what is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156165:10"/>the thing they ayme at, which is pillage, and baggage, and plundering, and the way which they would come by it is mundering, and deſtroying, &amp; therfore it wil come in very properly, to incourage you to that work, which theſe two noble Lords have ſo well opened to you, which is, the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon your defence; and to that I ſhall only add this, that when you ſhall have done that in that meaſure, and in that proportion, (which we do not doubt but you will doe, becauſe you have alwayes ſhew'd your affections, and your wiſedomes, to bee ſo great in the cariage on of this buſineſſe, I ſay, when you ſhall have ſo behaved your ſelves,) there is no doubt but Gods bleſſing will bee upon it, and you will be ſure to have an extraordinary back, you will bee ſure to have an extraordinary aſſiſtance, for the Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> with the whole Army, will bee ſure to bee on the one ſide, when you with your defence wil be on the other ſide, and when that Army ſhall lye betweene theſe two, without queſtion they will come to a very ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, when you may reap the fruit of your labours that you have beene at, to your benefit, and your poſterities. <hi>Finis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Earle of Holland his ſecond ſpeeth</head>
            <p>MY Lord Maior and Gentlemen, it is but a word or two that I ſhall ſay to you, for the ſhutting up of this; the danger hath heene repreſented to you, we muſt deſire you likewiſe to conſider how neere it moves, that you muſt reſolve and act both together; they conceiv this Army will be at <hi>Oxford</hi> as this night, that is within ſuch a diſtance, as within threee dayes they may march to <hi>London,</hi> it is very neceſſary for you to provide againſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156165:11"/>this, as a danger that may bee very ſuddenly upon you, if they ſhould chance to march before the other Army, and with ſuch an advantage, as to breake up bridges, or any ſuch thing, as may hinder the other Army to move pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, and ſuddenly after them. Conſider how open you are to this danger, if you provide not preſently for it, therefore as we have given you reaſons, and indeed as you may take almoſt from your owne reaſons to defend your ſelves) that it will be very neceſſary for you, to look upon this as a danger, that you wil not loſe an hour for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding againſt, and that is all I ſhall ſay unto you. <hi>Finis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <head>The Earle of Pembrook his ſecond ſpeech.</head>
            <p>MY Lord Maior, and you Gentlemen, I ſhall onely ſpeake one word to you, and that concernes your ſelves moſt neareſt, and you know them better than I a great deale, though I have beene a long time bred in the City for many yeares, truly you that are Citizens, muſt know it better than I, you know you have a great malignant partie in the Citie, you have now time and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to looke to them, leave no time to looke into it, for if you leave that till a time of diſtraction, they will bee a great deale bolder than now they are, now you may doe it in time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:156165:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
